<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ENTITY eacute	"&#x00E9;"> <!-- LATIN SMALL LETTER E WITH ACUTE -->
<!ENTITY zcaron	"&#x017E;"> <!-- LATIN SMALL LETTER Z WITH CARON -->
]> 
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI Bylaws</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>28 Nov 2000</date> Final draft</edition>
      </editionStmt>    

      <publicationStmt>
        <p> Part of the Official TEI Consortium Website</p>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Derived from various documents and drafts</p>
      </sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>      
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
<body>
<p>The bylaws presented here are those proposed at the time of
incorporation. They may be revised by the TEI Board, as
further described <ref target="TEIby-A7">herein</ref>. The bylaws also
specify different <ref target="TEIby-A1">classes of membership</ref>
available, and other details of the organizational structure of the
Consortium, such as its <ref target="TEIby-A4">Board of Directors</ref> and
<ref target="TEIby-A6">Committees</ref>. For full details, please consult
the table of contents for this section.</p>

<div type="art" id="TEIby-A1"><head>Article I. Members</head>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A1.1"><head>1. Members.</head>
<list type="ordered gloss">
<label>Classes of Members</label>

<item>Institutions, consortia,
organizations, projects and companies can be members of the TEI-C. There shall be one class
of members. Each member shall be entitled to one vote for each
director position to be elected and for any other vote requiring
the vote of the members, as specified in Article II, section 3 of
these bylaws. Members will have the right, also, to propose
officially sanctioned TEI-C training and services, with such
agreements screened by the TEI-C Council and approved, ultimately,
by the TEI-C Board of Directors.</item>
<label>Subscribers and Sponsors</label>
<item>In addition to members, the TEI-C shall have subscribers and
sponsors. Subscribers and sponsors will pay dues and will enjoy
many of the benefits that members enjoy, but they will not
vote.</item>
<label>Application</label>
<item>Any organization eligible to become a member (and any
individual or organization eligible to become a subscriber or
sponsor) of The TEI-C may apply by submitting an application, in
form prescribed by the Board of Directors, along with any dues or
filing fees required to be submitted with an application, to the
Secretary of the TEI-C. If the Secretary finds that such applicant
has complied with all requirements in connection with the
application, the Secretary shall add the applicant's name to the
list of members (or subscribers or sponsors).</item>
<label>Dues, Etc</label>
<item>Members (and subscribers and sponsors) shall pay dues (and
such other charges and assessments as are established by the Board
of Directors) in such amounts and at such intervals as determined
by the Board of Directors from time to time. The Directors may
establish differences among members (or subscribers or sponsors)
with respect to the amount or timing of dues or other charges or
assessments. Notice of any dues increase approved by the Board of
Directors shall be provided to members, subscribers and sponsors at
least 60 days prior to the annual billing date for dues. No member (or subscriber or sponsor) shall be
entitled to a refund of any dues or other charges or assessments
upon resignation or termination.</item>
<label>Special Categories</label>
<item>The Board may from time to time establish special categories
to recognize outstanding contributions by members. The development
of tools that further the use of TEI, for example, may entitle a
member to be designated as a TEI Developer or other title which, in
the discretion of the Board, appropriately reflects such member's
contribution.</item>
         </list>
</div>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A1.2"><head> 2. Membership Requirements.</head>
<p> The Board may establish such
attendance and other requirements as it deems proper.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A1.3"><head>3. Duration.</head>
<p> Each member may hold membership as long as
such member remains qualified for membership, except that
membership may be sooner terminated by suspension or expulsion as
provided in Section 3 of this Article or by resignation as provided
in Section 4 of this Article.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A1.4"><head>4. Termination. </head>
<p> The Board of Directors may terminate a
membership (or subscribership or sponsorship) in the TEI-C upon a
good-faith finding of (a) misconduct by such member (or subscriber
or sponsor) reflecting discredit upon the TEI-C or (b) violation of
these Bylaws (including but not limited to the nonpayment of dues
or other required charges or assessments).</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A1.5"><head>5. Resignation. </head>
<p>Any member (or subscriber or sponsor)
may resign from the Consortium by delivering written notice of
resignation to the Secretary. Such resignation shall be effective
upon the Secretary's receipt of such written notice.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A2"><head>Article II:  Meetings of Members</head>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A2.1"><head>1. Meetings.</head>
<p> Meetings of the members shall be held not
less than once a year, on such dates and at such places as the
Board of Directors may designate from time to time. The first
meeting after December 31st shall be designated as the annual meeting. At
the annual meeting, the Chair shall report on the operation of the
TEI-C for the preceding year and announce the results of the
election of the Board of Directors.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A2.2"><head>2. Special Meetings.</head>
<p>A special meeting of members may be
called by the Board of Directors in its discretion or upon written
request to the Secretary by one-third or more of members of the
TEI-C entitled to vote. No business other than that specified in
the notice of the meeting shall be transacted at any special
meeting of the members. The notice of each annual meeting shall
include a proxy for the election of the members of the Board and
such other matters as may require the vote of the membership. The
proxies shall be returned to the Secretary, either in person,
dispatched by major courier service guaranteed for delivery in
three days or less, electronically mailed, or mailed by first class
(domestic) or airmail (international) post, postage-prepaid. The
Secretary will tabulate the results of the matters on which a vote
is taken. To be included in the tabulation of the vote, a proxy
must be received by the time designated in the material sent with
the notice of meeting. The final vote will be presented to the
members at its annual meeting by the Secretary either in person or
by certificate delivered to the Chair of the TEI-C. The vote by
proxy for the election of the Board shall be final. As to matters
other than the election of the Board, the votes for and against
each item by proxy will be presented at the annual meeting and
provisions made for those present to participate in a discussion
and vote on such items, changing the earlier vote by proxy if
desired.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A2.3"><head> 3. Voting.</head>
<p> At meetings of the members, members shall be
entitled to voting rights as provided in Article I of these Bylaws.
Upon application for membership, it is the responsibility of each
member to designate an elector empowered to cast votes for that
member: only designated electors will be permitted to vote. In the
event that a member wishes to change its designated elector, the
original applicant for that member organization must deliver
written notice to the Secretary of the TEI-C, identifying (with
full contact information) both the original elector and the new
elector, and stating that electoral rights should be transferred
from the former to the latter. Such notice shall be given not less
than fourteen (14) days before the date of the first meeting in
which the member wishes its new elector to be entitled to vote.
Notice shall be deemed duly given when it has been either delivered
in person, dispatched by major courier service guaranteed for
delivery in three days or less, electronically mailed, or mailed by
first class (domestic) or airmail (international) post,
postage-prepaid, to the address of the Secretary of the TEI-C, as
it appears on the TEI-C web site. In the event that a member has
not designated an elector at least fourteen (14) days before a
meeting, the member's vote cannot be cast at that
meeting.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A2.4"><head> 4. Notice of Meetings. </head>
<p>Written notice stating the place,
day and hour of the meeting, and, in the case of a special meeting,
the purpose or purposes for which the meeting is called shall be
given not less than twenty-one (21) days nor more than sixty (60)
days before the date of the meeting (except as otherwise required
by law) by or at the direction of the Chair or the Secretary, or
the persons calling the meeting, to each member entitled to vote. A
notice shall be deemed duly given to a member when it is either
delivered in person, dispatched by major courier service guaranteed
for delivery in three days or less, electronically mailed, or
mailed by first class (domestic) or airmail (international) post,
postage-prepaid, to the address of such member as it appears on the
records of the TEI-C.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A2.5"><head> 5. Quorum.</head>
<p> A quorum at any meeting of the members,
whether annual, regular, or special, shall exist if at least
one-third of the members entitled to vote are present in person or
by proxy. The vote of a majority of the members entitled to vote
that are present in person or by proxy at a meeting at which a
quorum is present shall be necessary and sufficient for the
adoption of any matter voted upon by the members, unless a greater
vote of the members is required by law or these bylaws.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A3"><head>Article III: Officers</head>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A3.1"><head> 1. Selection of Officers.</head>
<p> The officers of the TEI-C
shall be elected by the Board of Directors and shall consist of a
Chair, a Vice-Chair, a Secretary, and a Treasurer. The Board of
Directors may also select additional officers as it deems necessary
or appropriate from time to time. The officers of the TEI-C shall
have the respective powers set forth herein and as otherwise
provided by resolution of the Board of Directors. With the possible
exception of the treasurer, each officer of the TEI-C shall be
selected from among the Board of Directors. Notwithstanding any
other provision herein, the power to set salaries and fees of
employees and independent contractors shall reside in the Board of
Directors and not in any officer or officers.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A3.2"><head>2. Chair</head>
<p>The Chair shall be the chief executive officer of the TEI-C
and shall, subject to the direction of the Board of Directors,
generally supervise and manage the affairs of the TEI-C. In
general, the Chair shall perform all duties customary to the office
of Chair, shall see that all orders and resolutions of the Board of
Directors are carried out, and shall oversee the other officers in
the discharge of their duties. The Chair shall, if present, preside
at all meetings of the Board of Directors and of the members.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A3.3"><head>3. Vice-chair.</head>
<p>  In the absence of the Chair, the
Vice-chair shall carry out the Chair's duties at meetings. In
the event the position of Chair becomes vacant, the Vice-chair
shall carry out the Chair's duties as set forth in Section 2,
above, until the Board elects or appoints a successor Chair.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A3.4"><head>4. Secretary. </head>
<p>The Secretary shall keep the minutes of
all meetings of the members and of the Board of Directors, shall
serve all notices, shall present all pertinent communications
before the proper committees, shall be custodian of the records,
shall attest the seal of the TEI-C on all contracts and agreements
required by law to be under seal as authorized by the Board of
Directors, shall conduct the correspondence incident to this office
and shall perform such other duties as the Board of Directors may
require.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A3.5"><head>5. Treasurer. </head>
<p>The Treasurer shall collect, have custody
of and be responsible for all funds of the TEI-C, shall keep an
accurate account of such funds, shall pay all just bills when due
and funds are available, and shall submit a financial report as of
the end of each fiscal year (December 31st) at the annual
meeting. All checks, drafts, notices and orders for the payment of
money issued by the TEI-C and other similar documents requiring the
signature of the TEI-C shall be signed by the Treasurer or by such
other person or persons, if any, as the Board of Directors may from
time to time designate. In the event that the Treasurer is not
selected from among the Board of Directors, the Treasurer shall
become a member of the Board.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A4"><head>Article IV:  Board of Directors</head>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.1"><head>1. Directors. </head>
<p>The Board of Directors shall initially
consist of a minimum of seven (7) Directors and a maximum of nine
(9), and thereafter may be increased or decreased within the
foregoing range from time to time by a majority vote of the Board
of Directors then in office, or by members. The TEI Editor (or
Editors) shall be included in meetings of the Board as ex officio
members. Four of the Directors will be representatives of the TEI
Hosts: in the event that the TEI-C has more than four Hosts, the
Hosts will choose their representatives to the Board by simple
majority vote among themselves. Other Directors will normally be
elected by the members, except during the first two years of the
TEI-C, when the three scholarly societies that originally sponsored
development of the TEI (the Association for Literary and Linguistic
Computing, the Association for Computers and the Humanities, and
the Association for Computational Linguistics) will each have the
option to appoint a representative to the Board of Directors. In
the event that the appointive option of any of the Hosts or the
original sponsoring societies is not exercised, the resulting
vacancy on the Board shall be filled by a vote of members in normal
or special elections. Individuals need not be TEI-C sponsors or
subscribers or constituents of TEI-C members in order to be
nominated and elected to serve on the Board of Directors. The
minimum and maximum numbers of Directors may be changed, either to
different minimum and/or maximum numbers or to a single fixed
number, only by the members. No decrease in the number of Directors
shall affect the tenure of any incumbent Director. Any vacancy in a
Director position resulting from the increase in the number of
Directors shall be filled by the members, in normal or special
elections. Vacancies in a Director position resulting from other
causes shall be filled by the vote of members in normal or special
elections.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.2"><head> 2. Term and Class.</head>
<p> Each Director shall be elected for a
term of two (2) years, or in the case of election to fill a vacancy
between regular elections, for the term remaining for such vacant
position, except as provided in Section 1, above. The Board of
Directors shall consist of two classes of Directors (appointed and
elected) with each class being as nearly equal to the other class
as possible.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.3"><head> 3. Elections. </head>
<p>At each annual meeting the members will elect members to any of the
elected positions on the Board of Directors due to be vacated. Terms
of office begin at the following January 1st. Elected Directors will
serve a two-year term ending on December 31. In the election of
Directors each elected Director position shall be voted on as a
separate matter with each member entitled to vote receiving one vote
for each Director position.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.4"><head> 4. Meetings. </head>
<p>Regular meetings of the Board of Directors
may be held at such time and place as the Board of Directors may by
resolution designate. Directors may attend Board meetings by
telephonic or other two-way connection provided that the
Director(s) not physically present can hear, and be heard by, all
those participating in such meeting, and a Director so
participating shall be deemed present for quorum purposes. One of
such meetings, as close in time as may be practicable to the annual
meeting of the members, shall be designated by the Board as the
annual meeting of the Board. Special meetings may be called by the
Chair or any combination of Directors constituting at least
one-third of the total number of Directors then in office. In the
case of a special meeting of the Board of Directors, no business
other than that specified in the notice of the meeting shall be
transacted, unless all members of the Board are present at such
meeting and consent to the transaction of such other business.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.5"><head> 5. Quorum.</head>
<p> A majority of the Directors shall constitute
a quorum for the transaction of business. The act of the majority
of the Directors present at a meeting at which a quorum is present
shall be the act of the Board of Directors, unless a greater vote
of the Directors is required by law or these Bylaws, or pursuant to
the Members' Agreement. In lieu of action at a normal or
special meeting, the Board may act pursuant to unanimous written
consent signed by all Directors in one or more counterparts which
together shall constitute a single instrument, and the Board may
authorize, to the extent consistent with the laws of the
Commonwealth of Virginia, the use of secure electronic signatures
to sign such instruments if circulated by electronic mail.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A4.6"><head> 6. Notice of Meetings. </head>
<p>Written notice of all meetings of
the Board of Directors shall be required. Written notice shall be
given at least seven (7) days prior to regular meetings and at
least fourteen (14) days prior to special meetings. The notice
shall state the date, time, and place of the meeting and the
purpose thereof. A notice shall be deemed duly given when it is
either delivered in person, dispatched by a major courier service
guaranteeing delivery in three days or less, electronically mailed,
or mailed by first class (domestic) or airmail (international)
post, postage prepaid, to the address of such Directors as it
appears on the records of the TEI-C.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A5"><head>Article V:  Funds</head>
<p>Funds for meeting the expenses of the TEI-C may be provided in
such manner as the Board of Directors may determine, including
without limitation such annual or other periodic membership dues as
may be fixed from time to time by the Board of Directors and
specified in a Membership Agreement to be signed by each new member
of the TEI-C, and such charges for meetings, seminars, and
publications as may be fixed from time to time by the Board of
Directors. Charges other than for membership dues and assessments
may be set on a per-person basis or any other basis deemed
appropriate by the Board of Directors.</p>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A6"><head>Article VI: Committees  </head>
<div type="clause" id="TEIby-A6.1"><head> 1. Committees. </head>
<p>Except as provided otherwise herein, the
Board of Directors from time to time may appoint such committees as
it deems necessary to carry out the purposes of the TEI-C,
including but not limited to any committees described in these
Bylaws. These committees shall be assigned the responsibilities
described in these Bylaws or specified by the Board of Directors
and shall report to the Board of Directors and/or the members as
required herein or by the Board of Directors.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A6.2"><head> 2. TEI-C Council.</head>
<p> The Board of Directors shall establish
a TEI-C Council to superintend the technical work of the TEI-C. The
TEI-C Council will consist of twelve members, who need not be TEI-C
sponsors or subscribers or constituents of TEI-C members. The TEI-C
Council membership shall include the Chair of the TEI-C Board of
Directors and one other member, and may include such other
Directors or members as designated by the Board of Directors. The
Chair of the TEI-C Council will be designated by the Board of
Directors. At least one TEI Editor should attend any
meeting of the TEI Council.</p>
<p>Except as specified in these bylaws or as designated by the Board
of Directors, TEI-C Council members will be elected to two-year terms
by TEI-C members, with nominations and service open to the general
public; at each annual meeting the members will elect members to any
of the elected positions on the TEI Council due to be vacated. Terms
of office begin at the following January 1st. Elected Council members
will serve a two-year term ending on December 31. In the election of
Council members each elected Council position shall be voted on as a
separate matter with each member entitled to vote receiving one vote
for each Council position.</p>
<p>The work of the TEI-C Council will be to
collect, propose, evaluate, and implement editorial changes to the
TEI DTD (and its derivatives), to produce up-to-date documentation
for the TEI, and to evaluate agreements for official TEI-C training
and services and make recommendations to the TEI-C Board concerning
endorsement of such training and services. The TEI-C Council may
delegate any of those functions to appointed working groups or
committees, at its discretion. The TEI-C Council will also have the
power to create working groups with a fixed term and a specific
charter, and to appoint or to delegate the appointment of the
membership of those working groups. The TEI-C Council may convene
upon call of the Chair or at the request of a majority of the
Board. A majority of the members of the TEI-C Council shall
constitute a quorum.</p>

</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A6.3"><head> 3. TEI-C Hosts.</head>
<p> Upon incorporation, the first four TEI-C
Hosts shall be Brown University (the Scholarly Technology Group),
the University of Virginia (the Institute for Advanced Technology
in the Humanities and the Electronic Text Center), Oxford
University (The Research Technologies Service<!--Humanities Computing Unit-->), and The University of
Bergen, represented by the<!-- HIT Centre of the Bergen University
Research Foundation-->Department of Culture, Language, and Information
    technology, each of whom shall serve a four-year term.
Thereafter, the Board of Directors shall select a minimum of four
TEI-C Hosts, using a public Request for Proposals process. Hosts
may be re-appointed for second and subsequent terms, but they must
participate in the RFP process. In the event that a Host
representative vacates one of the four Host seats on the TEI-C
Board and there are at that time more than four Hosts, the
remaining Hosts shall collectively select the replacement Board
member. In the event that there are fewer than four Hosts, the seat
on the Board shall be empty until filled by the normal Host
selection process. In selecting Hosts, the Board of Directors shall
respect those fundamental principles of the TEI-C calling for
international and interdisciplinary representation. Hosts must be
members of the TEI-C. Hosts shall serve for a minimum four-year
term, and shall agree, in addition to a membership fee, to provide
support services for the TEI-C and to organize, convene, or assist
in TEI-C meetings. Hosts may also assist the TEI-C in recruiting
members, raising endowment, providing training or consulting to
members, and disseminating information and tools relevant to the
use of TEI.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A6.4"><head> 4.  Editors. </head>
<p>The TEI Editor(s) shall be appointed by the TEI-C Board
<!--presumably (though not necessarily) from among the
TEI Council, --> for five year-terms. TEI Editors need not be TEI-C
sponsors or subscribers or constituents of TEI-C members. A TEI
Editor may be removed prior to the end of such term by vote of the
Board of Directors providing that the notice for the board meeting
at which such action is to be considered shall contain notice of
such proposed action. Editors may be reappointed to
consecutive terms.</p>
</div><div type="clause" id="TEIby-A6.5"><head> 5. Nominating Committee.</head>
<p> Not less than three months
prior to the notice date for each annual meeting of the members,
the Board of Directors shall appoint a Nominating Committee
consisting of two (2) or more of the Directors, one of whom the
Board shall designate as the Chair of the Nominating Committee. The
Nominating Committee shall solicit members and others for nominees,
and those nominating such candidates shall provide the Nominating
Committee with written confirmation that each candidate, if
elected, is willing to serve. Such candidates shall then be
included on the slate of candidates proposed by the Nominating
Committee. The Nominating Committee shall propose one or more
candidates for each Director and council position to be elected
pursuant to proxy sent to all members in connection with the notice
of the annual meeting. The slate of candidates proposed by the
Nominating Committee shall be contained in the notice of such
meeting. In addition, the Nominating Committee shall prepare the
slate of officers to be presented at the annual meeting of the
Board of Directors, soliciting Board members and others, to the
extent permitted in these Bylaws, for such positions and securing
written confirmation that each officer candidate, if elected, is
willing to serve. This slate of proposed officers shall be
contained in the notice of the annual meeting of Directors. Except
as otherwise provided in these Bylaws, in the event of a vacancy on
the Board of Directors or the Council, members shall, at a regular
or special meeting, elect a replacement to serve the remaining term
of such vacant position.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="art" id="TEIby-A7"><head>Article VII:  Amendments</head>
<p>These Bylaws may be repealed or amended or new Bylaws adopted by
affirmative vote of at least one-half of the members of TEI-C
voting in person or by proxy at a regular or special meeting, or,
to the extent permitted by law and not in conflict with the
Articles of Incorporation, by a true majority of the Board of
Directors then in office acting at a regular or special meeting, or
by unanimous written consent of the Board. With respect to any
meeting of members at which a Bylaw change is to be put to a vote,
notice of such proposed change to the Bylaws, including the text
thereof, shall be included in the notice given for such meeting.
With respect to any Board meeting at which a Bylaw change is to be
put to a vote, notice of such proposed Bylaw change, including the
text thereof, shall be given twenty-one (21) days before the date
of such meeting, by any of the various means set forth in Article
IV, above.</p>
</div>
<!--
<div type="coda" id="by-coda">
<p>The undersigned, being the duly elected Secretary of the TEI-C
hereby certifies that these Bylaws were adopted as the Bylaws of
the Consortium by a unanimous consent approved by all of the
Directors effective on December ___, 2000.</p>

<p>______________________</p>
<p>Secretary</p>

</div>
-->

</body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>


























