<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Bylaws</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition><date when="2023-08-12">12 August 2023</date></edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared by </resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Part of the official TEI Consortium Website</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Contents are derived from TEI Consortium website representation of the Bylaws in
               Wordpress in August 2023.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>From 2013 to 2023, the Bylaws were maintained in Wordpress which bears traces of the TEI
            header and its changelog from the version of 2013. As of 2023, the version in Wordpress
            was marked, <q>2013 Revision. Edited from online version, last updated 2011-08-09</q>,
            but it was amended in subsequent years, regrettably without a changelog due to the
            Wordpress format. Restoring these Bylaws to TEI format allows for more robust
            preservation of our consortium’s history and policies, in keeping with the principles of
            the TEI Consortium. In restoring the Bylaws to TEI, elements and structure for this 2023
            edition were chosen in consultation with the 2000 edition in TEI P4 and remnants of the
            changelog visible in the Wordpress encoding. XML comments visible in the Wordpress
            encoding are restored here.</p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2013">2013 Revision. Edited from online version, last updated 2011-08-09.
               Corrections and comments from <persName>Kevin</persName> and
                  <persName>Brett</persName>. Revised and simplified for presentation and vote at
               2013 Members Meeting.</change>
            <change when="2011-01-19">Friday, 19 January, 2011. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Copied approved Language to official site.</change>
            <change when="2011-01-12">Wednesday, 12 January, 2011. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Added overlooked language on officer terms.</change>
            <change when="2011-01-07">Friday, 07 January, 2011. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Implemented changes recommended by the board upon adoption
               in principle at November meeting.</change>
            <change when="2010-10-08">Friday, 8 October, 2010. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Edited proposal to reflect suggestions from Board
               discussion.</change>
            <change when="2010-09-28">Wednesday, 28 September, 2010. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Initial proposals for implementing approval in principle of
               reorganisation of board and hosts as approved in email vote ending on September 25,
               2010.</change>
            <change when="2007-12-19">Wednesday, 19 December, 2007. <persName>Daniel Paul
                  O'Donnell</persName>. Finalised text as approved by board at bm23.</change>
            <change when="2007-11-26">Thursday, 26 November 2007. <persName>Chris
               Ruotolo</persName>. Changed text as suggested by <persName>Julia
               Flanders</persName>.</change>
            <change when="2007-11-22">Thursday, 22 November 2007, 20:25 MST. <persName>Dan
                  O'Donnell</persName> changed text as proposed by SB and did comparison with
               original bylaws to make sure all differences are noted.</change>
            <change when="2007-11-18">Sunday, 18 November 07, 12:13 MST. <persName>Dan
                  O'Donnell</persName> changed text as proposed by SR and LB.</change>
            <change when="2007-11-17">Saturday, 17 November 07. <persName>Dan O'Donnell</persName>
               Proposed deletions and revisions to 2000-11-28 final draft. </change>
            <change when="2007-08-24">Thu, 24 Aug 07. <persName>Chris Ruotolo</persName> Converted
               to TEI P5.</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>TEI Bylaws</head>
            <p>These Bylaws are those proposed at the time of incorporation as subsequently revised.
               They may be revised further by the TEI Board, as described in <ref target="#TEIby-A7"
                  >Article 7</ref> below. The Bylaws specify <ref target="#TEIby-A1">classes of
                  membership</ref>, <ref target="#TEIby-A2">conduct of meetings of the Consortium
                  Members</ref>, <ref target="#TEIby-A3">appointment and responsibilities of
                  Consortium Officers</ref>, <ref target="#TEIby-A4">constitution and
                  responsibilities of the Board of Directors</ref>, <ref target="#TEIby-A6"
                  >constitution and responsibilities of the Technical Council</ref>, and <ref
                  target="#TEIby-A5">funding of Consortium activities</ref>.</p>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A1">
               <head>Article I. Members</head>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A1.1">
                  <head>1. Classes of Membership.</head>
                  <p>There shall be two classes of membership in the TEI Consortium: individual
                     membership and institutional membership. Any form of institution, consortium,
                     organization, project or company may become an Institutional Member. Only
                     private individuals may become Individual Members. Institutional Members shall
                     have the right to vote in all TEI elections, in particular to elect members of
                     the TEI Board of Directors and to elect members of the TEI Technical Council.
                     Individual Members shall have the right to elect members of the TEI Technical
                     Council. Both classes of Member shall be equally eligible for such other
                     membership benefits as the TEI Board of Directors may determine from time to
                     time, including but not limited to preferential rates for attendance at
                     TEI-sponsored events, discounted rates for purchase of TEI-related services or
                     software, or similar.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A1.2">
                  <head>2. Application and Dues.</head>
                  <p>Any organization or individual wishing to become a Member of the TEI Consortium
                     may apply by submitting an application, in form prescribed by the Board of
                     Directors to the Secretary of the Consortium or other Officer. Individual and
                     Institutional Members shall pay membership dues in such amounts and at such
                     intervals as determined by the Board of Directors from time to time. Notice of
                     any dues increase approved by the Board of Directors shall be provided to
                     Members at least 60 days prior to the annual billing date for dues. No Member
                     shall be entitled to a refund of any dues or other charges or assessments upon
                     resignation or termination.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A1.3">
                  <head>3. Duration.</head>
                  <p>Each Member may hold membership as long as such Member remains qualified for
                     membership, except that membership may be sooner terminated by suspension or
                     expulsion as provided in <ref target="#TEIby-A1.4">Clause 4</ref> of this
                     Article or by resignation as provided in <ref target="#TEIby-A1.5">Clause
                        5</ref> of this Article.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A1.4">
                  <head>4. Termination.</head>
                  <p>The Board of Directors may terminate a membership in the Consortium upon a
                     good-faith finding of (a) misconduct by such Member reflecting discredit upon
                     the Consortium or (b) violation of these Bylaws (including but not limited to
                     the nonpayment of dues or other required charges or assessments).</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A1.5">
                  <head>5. Resignation.</head>
                  <p>Any Member may resign from the Consortium by delivering written notice of
                     resignation to the Secretary. Such resignation shall be effective upon the
                     Secretary's receipt of such written notice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A2">
               <head>Article II: Meetings of Members</head>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.1">
                  <head>1. Meetings.</head>
                  <p>Meetings of the Members shall be held not less than once a year, on such dates
                     and at such places as the Board of Directors may designate from time to time.
                     The last meeting before December 31 in any year shall be designated the Annual
                     Meeting for that year. At the Annual Meeting, both the Board of Directors and
                     the Technical Council shall report to the membership on the operation of the
                     Consortium during the preceding year. The results of annual elections will also
                     be presented at this Annual Meeting.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.2">
                  <head>2. Special Meetings.</head>
                  <p>A Special Meeting of Members may be called by the Board of Directors at its
                     discretion or upon written request to the Secretary by one-third or more of the
                     Institutional Members of the Consortium. No business other than that specified
                     in the notice of the meeting shall be transacted at any Special Meeting of the
                     Members.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.3">
                  <head>3. Voting.</head>
                  <p>Members shall be entitled to voting rights as provided in Article I of these
                     Bylaws. Only designated Electors shall be permitted to vote. For Individual
                     Members, the Member shall be the Elector and their vote is not transferable to
                     any other person, except by means of a Proxy as defined below.For Institutional
                     Members, a named individual, specified at the time of taking up or renewing
                     membership shall be designated the Elector. It is the responsibility of the
                     Institutional Member to ensure that the Secretary of the Consortium is provided
                     with a current contact address for its Elector. In the event that a member
                     wishes to change its designated Elector, the original applicant for that
                     Institutional Member must deliver written notice to the Secretary of the
                     Consortium, identifying (with full contact information) both the original
                     Elector and the new Elector, and stating that electoral rights should be
                     transferred from the former to the latter. Such notice shall be given not less
                     than fourteen (14) days before the date of the first Meeting in which the
                     member wishes its new Elector to be entitled to vote. In the event that an
                     Institutional Member has designated neither an Elector nor a Proxy at least
                     fourteen (14) days before a Meeting, the Member's vote shall not be cast at
                     that Meeting.A Member may designate a Proxy voter. Where votes are to be cast
                     by means of a Proxy, details of that Proxy shall be returned to the Secretary
                     by the time designated in the material sent with the notice of Meeting, as
                     defined in <ref target="#TEIby-A2.4">Clause 4 below</ref>.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.4">
                  <head>4. Notice of Meetings.</head>
                  <p>A written notice stating the place, day and hour of the Meeting, and, in the
                     case of a Special Meeting, the purpose or purposes for which the Meeting is
                     called ("Notice") shall be given not less than twenty-one (21) days nor more
                     than sixty (60) days before the date of the Meeting to each designated Elector
                     entitled to vote at the Meeting.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.5">
                  <head>5. Quorum.</head>
                  <p>A quorum is required before any vote may be taken at any Meeting of the Members
                     The quorum required shall be one-third of the total number of Members entitled
                     to vote. The number of Electors present in person or by proxy, or having
                     previously cast a vote by electronic ballot, shall constitute the quorum.Where
                     a quorum is present, the vote of a majority of the Members entitled to vote at
                     a Meeting shall be necessary and sufficient for the adoption of any matter
                     voted upon by the Members, unless a greater vote of the Members is required by
                     law or these Bylaws. In the event quorum is not achieved at a Meeting of the
                     Members, the issue in question may be passed to the Board for resolution or
                     deferred to a subsequent Meeting of the Members.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A2.6">
                  <!-- was xml:id="TEIby-A6.5" -->
                  <head>6. Nominating Committee.</head>
                  <p>Not less than three months prior to the notice date for each Annual Meeting of
                     the Members, the Board of Directors shall appoint a Nominating Committee
                     consisting of two (2) or more of the Directors, one of whom the Board shall
                     designate as the Chair of the Nominating Committee.The Nominating Committee
                     shall solicit Members and others for nominees, and those nominating such
                     candidates shall provide the Nominating Committee with written confirmation
                     that each candidate, if elected, is willing to serve. Such candidates shall
                     then be included on the slate of candidates proposed by the Nominating
                     Committee. The Nominating Committee shall propose candidates for each vacancy
                     on the Board of Directors and Technical Council. The slate of candidates
                     proposed by the Nominating Committee shall be contained in the notice of the
                     Annual Meeting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A3">
               <head>Article III: Officers</head>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A3.1">

                  <head>1. Officers of the Consortium.</head>
                  <p>The following Officers shall discharge the affairs of the Consortium: <list
                        rend="bulleted">
                        <item>Chair of the Board</item>
                        <item>Chair of the Technical Council</item>
                        <item>Board Secretary</item>
                        <item>Membership Secretary</item>
                        <item>Treasurer</item>
                     </list> Unless otherwise stated in these Bylaws, the Board of Directors may
                     appoint Officers from its own membership or elsewhere and may also appoint such
                     additional non-voting Officers as it deems necessary or appropriate from time
                     to time.</p>

                  <p>The Officers of the Consortium shall have the respective powers set forth
                     herein and as otherwise provided by resolution of the Board of Directors.
                     Notwithstanding any other provision herein, the power to set salaries and fees
                     of employees and independent contractors shall reside in the Board of Directors
                     and not in any Officer or Officers.</p>

                  <p>All Officers of the Consortium shall be appointed for a maximum term of two
                     years with possibility of reelection to subsequent two-year terms.</p>

               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A3.2">
                  <head>2. Chair of the Board.</head>
                  <p>The Chair of the Board shall be elected by the Board of Directors from its
                     membership and shall serve as the chief executive officer of the Consortium. If
                     no Director is able or willing to assume the chair, the Directors may request
                     the Technical Council to second one of its elected members to the role, or it
                     may nominate a non-elected individual.Subject to the direction of the Board of
                     Directors, the Chair will generally supervise and manage the affairs of the
                     Consortium. In general, the Chair shall perform all duties customary to the
                     office of Chair, shall see that all orders and resolutions of the Board of
                     Directors are carried out, and shall oversee the other Officers in the
                     discharge of their duties. The Chair shall, if present, preside at all meetings
                     of the Board of Directors and of the Members.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <!-- was xml:id="TEIby-A3.5" -->
                  <head>3. Chair of the Technical Council.</head>
                  <p>The Chair of the Technical Council shall be elected by the voting Members of
                     the <ref target="#TEIby-A6">TEI-C Technical Council</ref> from its membership
                     and shall serve as the chief technical officer of the Consortium. If no
                     Technical Council Member is able or willing to assume the chair, the Technical
                     Council may request the Board of Directors to second one of its elected members
                     to the role, or it may nominate a non-elected individual.The Chair of the
                     Technical Council shall be an ex-officio non-voting Director, responsible to
                     the Consortium for its technical activities, notably the maintenance and
                     development of the Guidelines.The Council Chair shall, if present, preside at
                     all meetings of the Technical Council and report on its activities to the Board
                     of Directors and at Meetings of the Members.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <!-- was xml:id="TEIby-A3.3"-->
                  <head>4. Board Secretary.</head>
                  <p>The Board Secretary shall be elected by the Board of Directors from its
                     membership. The Secretary shall keep the minutes of all Meetings of the Members
                     and of the Board of Directors, serve all notices, present all pertinent
                     communications before the proper committees, shall be custodian of the records,
                     shall attest the seal of the Consortium on all contracts and agreements
                     required by law to be under seal as authorized by the Board of Directors, shall
                     conduct the correspondence incident to this office and shall perform such other
                     duties as the Board of Directors may require.In the absence of the Chair, the
                     Secretary shall carry out the Chair's duties at meetings. In the event the
                     position of Chair becomes vacant, the secretary shall carry out the Chair's
                     duties as set forth above, until the Board elects or appoints a successor
                     Chair.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <!-- was xml:id="TEIby-A3.6" -->
                  <head>5. Membership Secretary.</head>
                  <p>The Membership Secretary shall be responsible for the recruitment and
                     maintenance of the Member rolls and direction and development of membership
                     benefits and programmes. The Membership Secretary shall assist the Treasurer in
                     annual invoicing. In addition to day-to-day activity, the Membership Secretary
                     shall also be responsible for the strategic development of the membership.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <!-- xml:id="TEIby-A3.4" -->
                  <head>6. Treasurer.</head>
                  <p>The Treasurer shall collect, have custody of and be responsible for all funds
                     of the Consortium, shall keep an accurate account of such funds, shall pay all
                     just bills when due and funds are available, and shall prepare and submit such
                     financial reports as are legally required by the fiscal authorities. In
                     addition the Treasurer shall report to the Membership on the financial affairs
                     of the Consortium during the past year at the Annual Meeting. All checks,
                     drafts, invoices, notices and orders for the payment or receipt of money issued
                     by the Consortium and other similar documents requiring the signature of the
                     Consortium shall be signed by the Treasurer or by such other person or persons
                     as the Board of Directors may from time to time designate for this purpose.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A4">
               <head>Article IV: Board of Directors</head>
               <p>The TEI Board of Directors shall determine overall policy directions for the
                  Consortium and is also responsible for managing and promoting membership in the
                  Consortium.</p>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.1">
                  <head>1. Directors.</head>
                  <p>The Board of Directors shall consist of no more than five (5) voting Directors,
                     <!-- no minimum is stated... --> elected by the membership as described in <ref
                        target="#TEIby-A2">Article II</ref>. Additional non-voting appointments to
                     the Board may be made by the Board as necessary for the efficient conduct of
                     its business. Only Board Directors elected by the membership as described in
                        <ref target="#TEIby-A2">Article II</ref> shall be eligible to vote in Board
                     decisions.Candidates need not be Individual Members of the Consortium in order
                     to be nominated and elected to serve on the Board of Directors, nor need they
                     be affiliated with an Institutional Member of the Consortium.No decrease in the
                     number of elected Directors shall affect the tenure of any incumbent Director.
                     Any vacancy among the elected membership of the Board shall be filled by the
                     vote of Members in normal or special elections.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.2">
                  <head>2. Term.</head>
                  <p>Each Director shall be elected for a term of three (3) years, or in the case of
                     election or appointment to fill a vacancy between regular elections, for the
                     term remaining for the vacant position. Terms of office begin at the following
                     January 1 and end on December 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.3">
                  <head>3. Elections.</head>
                  <p>At each Annual Meeting the Institutional Members shall elect candidates to any
                     of the elected positions on the Board of Directors due to be vacated. In the
                     election of Directors each elected position shall be voted on as a separate
                     matter with each member entitled to vote receiving one vote for each such
                     position.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.4">
                  <head>4. Meetings.</head>
                  <p>Meetings of the Board of Directors may be held at such time and place as the
                     Board of Directors may by resolution designate. Directors may attend Board
                     meetings by telephonic or other two-way connection provided that any Director
                     not physically present can hear, and be heard by, all those participating in
                     such meeting, and a Director so participating shall be deemed present for
                     quorum purposes.Special meetings may be called by the Chair or any combination
                     of Directors constituting at least one-third of the total number of Directors
                     then in office. In the case of a special meeting of the Board, no business
                     other than that specified in the notice of the meeting shall be transacted,
                     unless all members of the Board are present at such meeting and consent to the
                     transaction of such other business.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.5">
                  <head>5. Quorum.</head>
                  <p>A majority of the elected Directors shall constitute a quorum for the
                     transaction of business.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="TEIby-A4.6">
                  <head>6. Notice of Meetings.</head>
                  <p>Notice of all meetings of the Board of Directors shall be required at least
                     seven (7) days prior to regular meetings and at least fourteen (14) days prior
                     to special meetings. The notice shall state the date, time, and place of the
                     meeting and the purpose thereof and shall be delivered to each Director at the
                     address registered for them by the Secretary.</p>
                  <!-- what about public announcement? -->
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A5">
               <head>Article V: Funds</head>
               <p>Funds for meeting the expenses of the Consortium may be provided in such manner as
                  the Board of Directors may determine, including without limitation such annual or
                  other periodic membership dues as may be fixed from time to time by the Board of
                  Directors and specified in a Membership Agreement to be signed by each new Member
                  of the Consortium, and such charges for meetings, seminars, and publications as
                  may be fixed from time to time by the Board of Directors. Charges other than for
                  membership dues and assessments may be set on a per-person basis or any other
                  basis deemed appropriate by the Board of Directors.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A6">
               <head>Article VI: Technical Council</head>
               <p>The Technical Council shall superintend the technical work of the Consortium, in
                  particular (but not only) by monitoring, evaluating, and acting upon requests from
                  the TEI Community for new features and correction of errors in the TEI
                  Guidelines.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>1. Membership.</head>
                  <p>The Technical Council shall consist of eleven (11) Council Members elected by
                     the membership, as described in <ref target="#TEIby-A2">Article II</ref>.
                     Additional non-voting Council Members may be appointed or co-opted as necessary
                     for the efficient conduct of business. Only Council Members elected by the
                     membership as described in <ref target="#TEIby-A2">Article II</ref> shall be
                     eligible to vote in Technical Council decisions. Candidates need not be
                     Individual Members of the Consortium in order to be nominated and elected to
                     serve on the Technical Council, nor need they be affiliated with an
                     Institutional Member of the Consortium.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>2. Term.</head>
                  <p>Each Technical Council Member shall be elected for a three-year term, or in the
                     case of an election or appointment to fill a vacancy between regular elections,
                     for the term remaining for the vacant position. Terms of office begin at the
                     following January 1 and end on December 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>3. Elections.</head>
                  <p>At each Annual Meeting both Institutional and Individual members shall elect
                     candidates to any of the elected positions due to be vacated on the Technical
                     Council. In the election of Council Members each elected position shall be
                     voted on as a separate matter with each Member entitled to vote receiving one
                     vote for each such position.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>4. Meetings.</head>
                  <p>Regular meetings of the Technical Council shall be held at such time and place
                     as necessary to carry out its work programme. The bulk of the Technical
                     Council's work programme shall be carried out by electronic or telephonic
                     means, but at least one meeting shall be held face to face each year. The
                     Technical Council may be convened upon call of the Chair, at the request of a
                     majority of its members, at a time and place designated by resolution of the
                     Technical Council. Council Members may attend Technical Council meetings by
                     telephonic or other two-way connection provided that those not physically
                     present can hear, and be heard by, all those participating in such meeting, and
                     a Council Member so participating shall be deemed present for quorum purposes.A
                     record of all business transacted at the meetings of the Technical Council
                     shall be kept, and shall be made publicly available.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>5. Quorum.</head>
                  <p>A majority of the elected Technical Council Members shall constitute a
                     quorum.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>6. Working Groups.</head>
                  <p>The work of the Technical Council shall be to collect, propose, evaluate, and
                     implement editorial changes to the TEI Guidelines (and its derivatives), to
                     assist in technical endeavours of the TEI-C, and to provide consultation to the
                     Board of Directors on technical matters or other areas of interest. The
                     Technical Council may delegate any of these functions to appointed working
                     groups or committees at its discretion. The Technical Council shall also have
                     the power to create working groups or appoint non-voting staff and advisors
                     with a fixed term and a specific charter. Where Consortium funding for such
                     workgroups or staff is required this shall be subject to prior approval of the
                     Board.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="TEIby-A7">
               <head>Article VII: Amendments</head>
               <p>These Bylaws may be repealed or amended or new Bylaws adopted by affirmative vote
                  of at least one-half of the Members of Consortium voting in person or by proxy at
                  a regular or Special Meeting, or, to the extent permitted by law and not in
                  conflict with the Articles of Incorporation, by a true majority of the Board of
                  Directors then in office acting at a regular or Special Meeting, or by unanimous
                  written consent of the Board. With respect to any Meeting of Members at which a
                  Bylaw change is to be put to a vote, notice of such proposed change to the Bylaws,
                  including the text thereof, shall be included in the notice given for such
                  Meeting. With respect to any Board meeting at which a Bylaw change is to be put to
                  a vote, notice of such proposed Bylaw change, including the text thereof, shall be
                  given twenty-one (21) days before the date of such Meeting, by any of the various
                  means set forth in <ref target="#TEIby-A2">Article II</ref>, above.</p>
            </div>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
