<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TCW09: Backward Compatibility and the Maintenance of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines</title>
        <author xml:id="djb">David J. Birnbaum</author>
        <editor>CJR</editor> <!-- identified as tagging this in TEI from David's email of 2006-08-02 -->
        <editor>Lou Burnard</editor><!-- identifed as convertng the document to TEI P5 -->
        <editor xml:id="EBB">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor> <!-- restoring this from the Wayback Machine on 2025-11-09 to store in the TEI Documentation GitHub repository-->
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Technical Council</publisher>
        <date>2018</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This document was resurrected from the WayBack Machine representing TCW 09 from the TEI WordPress website that has, as of 2025, been removed.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-09" who="#EBB">Restored the document by copying it from the WayBack Machine.</change>
     
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>TCW09: Backward Compatibility and the Maintenance of the Text Encoding 
        Initiative Guidelines</head>
      <p>At the May 2006 TEI Council Meeting in Kyoto, Council expressed an 
        interest in elaborating principles for further development of the TEI 
        guidelines. In particular, Council expressed an interest in reconciling 
        two potentially conflicting principles:
      <list type="ordered">
        <item>As new technologies permit us to improve the ability of the TEI 
          guidelines to serve the research needs of users, those new capabilities 
          should be made available to users. The TEI should not eschew better ways 
          of doing things for fear of breaking backward compatibility.</item>
        <item>Because breaking backward compatibility is unpopular with users, and 
          for good reason, the TEI should avoid doing so unless the benefits are 
          compelling.</item>
      </list></p>
      <p>Some Council members argued in Kyoto that our license to break backward 
        compatibility would be revoked once we signed off on P5; others felt 
        that Council (especially new Council members) would appreciate the 
        availability of guiding and stable principles that did not simply 
        prohibit breaking backward compatibility, but that indicated how and 
        when it should be permitted.</p>
      <p>It should be noted that documents developed with a particular schema 
        remain valid against that schema in perpetuity, and in this sense no 
        change to the TEI Guidelines breaks backward compatibility. On the other 
        hand, a user may wish to integrate new, emerging features into an 
        existing project without rendering existing encoded information invalid, 
        and may need to produce a new schema for that purpose. It is in this 
        context that backward compatibility with existing features of the user&#8217;s 
        original schema becomes particularly important.</p>
      <p>Finally, the TEI currently seems to make no use of the concept of 
        deprecated features, although such a concept may provide a compromise 
        that allows the TEI to adopt new structures without invalidating old ones.</p>
      

      <div xml:id="history">
        <head>History</head>
        <p>Relevant sources for determining a suitable policy include:
         <list type="bulleted">
           <item>TEI PCP1. <title>The Preparation of Text Encoding Guidelines</title>. Closing Statement 
             of the Vassar Planning Conference. Version of 13 November 1987. 
             <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/SC/teipcp1.gml"/> or 
             <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/SC/teipcp1.txt"/>.</item>
           <item>TEI EDP1. <title>Design Principles for Text Encoding Guidelines</title>. Version of 9 
             January 1990. <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edp01.gml"/></item>
           <item>TEI EDW57. <title>Procedures for Correcting Errors in the TEI Guidelines. </title>
             Version of July 23, 1994 (Revised July 27, 1994). 
             <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw57.htm"/></item>
           <item>TEI EDW48. <title>Procedures for Maintenance and Extension of the TEI 
               Guidelines</title>. Version of 21 May 1995. <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw48.htm"/></item>
         </list>
          None of these documents explicitly prohibits the breaking of backward compatibility, although 
          TEI EDW57 distinguishes corrigible errors from those that are not 
          corrigible according to (among other things) whether correction would 
          break backward compatibility. The editors are empowered to 
          implement changes needed to remove corrigible errors without further
          ado; if not, the proposed 
          correction must be <q>referred to TC</q> (i.e. to the <q>Technical [Review] Committee</q>,
          or presumably now the TEI Technical Council) for action. The
          historical record thus seems to 
          suggest an awareness that breaking backward compatibility might confer 
          sufficient benefit that it should not be prohibited, but  also that it should 
          not be undertaken without careful review.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="guidelines">
        <head>Proposed Guidelines</head>
        <p>A. The TEI Technical Council should not be constrained by a policy that bluntly
          prohibits breaking backward compatibility after the publication of
          P5 version 1.0.0. The Technical Council should instead feel authorized to break backward
          compatibility when the Technical Council concludes that the advantages of doing so
          outweigh the disadvantages.
        </p>
        <p>B. Wherever possible, the Technical Council should implement changes so that new
          schemas are supersets of old ones, and do not render invalid any
          documents that would have been valid before the implementation of
          the changes. The addition of an element to a class creates such a
          superset; removing an element from a class has the opposite effect.
        </p>
        <p>C. In extreme situations, where the Technical Council concludes that the utility
          of a component would be improved substantially by a revision that
          could break backward compatibility, Council should:
          <list type="instructions">
            <item>Create the necessary new structure (class, content model,
              etc.) under a new name.</item>
            <item>Deprecate but retain the structure it is intended to replace. 
              [Note: The TEI Technical Council subsequently adopted a deprecation mechanism that supersedes this: 
              <ref target="https://tei-c.org/documentation/tcw27/">TCW27</ref>]
              <list type="bulleted">
                <item>Deprecated structures determined to be in wide use might be maintained in perpetuity. 
                  Such a decision would reflect the Technical Council’s expert opinion that eliminating them 
                  would be too disruptive to existing projects to be entertained, while making clear that 
                  their employment in new projects does not conform to best practice.</item>
                <item>Deprecated structures determined not to be in wide use
                  might eventually (as discussed immediately below) be removed
                  from the Guidelines.</item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item>Council may break backward compatibility in a more
              substantial and comprehensive way (as happened with the
              transition to P4 to P5) with the transition to a new major
              TEI proposal version (e.g., P6 version 1.0.0, but not P5 99.99.0). Such transitions should
              only happen in response to the emergence of new technologies
              (e.g., the transition from SGML to XML) or the development of a
              new architecture that conveys substantial benefit (e.g., the
              development of the new class system). Historically, new major
              versions have emerged approximately every five years, but with P5 
              a new system of rolling major/minor versions has been adopted.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

