<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Building a TEI Release</title>
        <author xml:id="MDH">Martin Holmes</author>
        <author>James Cummings</author>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>
        <author>David Sewell</author>
	<author xml:id="KSH">Kevin Hawkins</author>
        <author xml:id="HC">Hugh Cayless</author>
        <author xml:id="PS">Peter Stadler</author>
        <author xml:id="EM">Elli Mylonas</author>
        <author xml:id="EBB">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</author>
        <author xml:id="RV">Raffaele Viglianti</author>
        <author xml:id="JL">Jessica H. Lu</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Technical Council</publisher>
        <date>2018</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This document was originally a section of tcw20.xml, but has now been spun off into its
          own document.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-02-13" who="#JL">Additional changes based on February 2020 release to make links visible, clarify release steps, confirm primacy of Paderborn Jenkins server.</change>
      <change when="2020-02-13" who="#JL">Update all references, and add links, to Jenkins servers. Revise instructions regarding release version numbers.</change>
      <change when="2020-02-10" who="#EBB">Update all references about ssh to the tei server to the new HumaNum server consistently. Correct small grammatical errors.</change>
      <change when="2019-02-04" who="#EM">Add updates and clarifications learned from last release.</change>
      <change when="2019-01-30" who="#PS">Add information about setting JAVA_HOME for updating the Debian packages</change>
      <change when="2019-01-29" who="#sb">Be explicit about contacting Jenkins maintainers ahead of time</change>
      <change when="2016-09-25" who="mt">Recommendations for issue handling that facilitate preparing the Release Notes.</change>
      <change when="2016-04-02" who="#MDH">Beginning edits arising out of the experiences
      releasing 3.0.0. More to come.</change>
      <change when="2016-03-16" who="#KSH">Fixed error in git command as just reported on
        tei-council</change>
      <change when="2016-02-23" who="#HC">Edits for new release process.</change>
      <change when="2015-12-14" who="#MDH">Updates for new Jenkins server subdomains.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-07" who="#MDH">Update for use of ant build process for oxygen-tei rather
        than the old .sh file.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-04" who="#MDH">More updates to account for the shift from SF SVN to
        GitHub.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-03" who="#MDH">Updates to account for the shift from SF SVN to
        GitHub.</change>
      <change when="2015-04-06" who="#MDH">Updates arising out of release process for 2.8.0.</change>
      <change when="2015-04-06" who="#KSH">Added link to http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/IRC</change>
      <change when="2015-04-04" who="#MDH">Updates to take account of oxygen-tei's move from Google
        Code to GitHub, along with a couple of other tweaks.</change>
      <change when="2014-01" who="#MDH">Updates for changes in procedure ahead of the 2.6.0
        release.</change>
      <change when="2013-11" who="#MDH">Updates following move of some code from SourceForge to
        GitHub, and automation of the P5 version number in output.</change>
      <change when="2012-10-25" who="#MDH">Updates following Primrose Path release
        experience.</change>
      <change when="2012-07-24" who="#KSH">Newsfeed blog is no longer in SourceForge.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-28" who="#KSH">A few changes based on messages to tei-council on
        2012-06-19 and 2012-06-20.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-19" who="#KSH">Improvements suggested by various Council members based on
        experiences with version 2.1.0.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-16" who="#KSH">Explained version numbers and added reminder about
        including readme file in announcement.</change>
      <change when="2012-02-02" who="#MDH">Document forked from tcw20.xml.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>This document aims to provide a set of detailed instructions enabling a "release
        technician" (the Council member tasked with implementing a new release of the TEI) to
        prepare for and manage the release process. It assumes that the new packages will be taken
        from one of the Jenkins servers rather than being built locally by the release technician.
        This is easier and more reliable, because we ensure that the Jenkins servers are regularly
        updated and are correctly configured to build the TEI products.</p>

      <div xml:id="githubPackages">
        <head>Packages on GitHub</head>
        <p>The TEI maintains a number of distinct repositories on GitHub under the
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC">TEIC</ref> organization. The main repository for developing the P5 Guidelines
          and associated schemas is <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI">TEIC/TEI</ref>, and the TEI Stylesheets, the code for
          the Roma web application, and the source code for the Oxygen TEI plugin can be found in
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>, 
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Roma">TEIC/Roma</ref>, and
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei">TEIC/oxygen-tei</ref> respectively. </p>
        <p>The rest of this section describes how to make a new release for the main
            <ident>P5</ident> package, but similar procedures apply to the others. The instructions
          assume you are working on a Linux or MacOSX system with a command line, and know (more or
          less) how to do basic command-line operations such as running scripts and logging into a
          server with ssh.</p>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="beforeStarting">
        <head>What you will need before you start</head>

        <list type="bulleted">
          <item>An account on GitHub, and committer privileges over the TEI repository. If you have
            ever pushed a change to the TEI repository, you should have all the
            required permissions.</item>
          <item>Shell access on the TEI SourceForge project. Contact one of the admins to have this
            turned on. Normal committers don't have shell access.</item>
          <item> The release manager will need SSH login access to the tei account on the tei-c.org
            server. This involves two steps: <list type="ordered">
              <item>Generate an SSH key pair (if you don't have one already). If this is new to you,
                look at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ssh-keygen"
                  >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ssh-keygen</ref>.</item>

              <item>Send the public key to the Council Chair, who will forward it on to the system
                administrator.</item>
            </list> Make sure you get this set up well in advance of the release day, and make sure
            you can ssh tei@cchum-kvm-dockerteic.in2p3.fr successfully. </item>

          <item>Some familiarity with the three TEI Jenkins Continuous Integration Servers.
              <list type="ordered">
                <item><ref target="https://jenkins.tei-c.org">https://jenkins.tei-c.org</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="https://jenkins2.tei-c.org">https://jenkins2.tei-c.org</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="https://jenkins3.tei-c.org">https://jenkins3.tei-c.org</ref></item>
              </list>
            Take a little time to watch them work, and see how a push to the GitHub
            repository causes them to start building TEI packages. There are three specific build
            jobs associated with P5, and they run in a fixed sequence. Currently, as of February 2020,
            the actual build for the release will rely on the first Jenkins server, often referred to as
            the "Paderborn Jenkins" (maintained by Peter Stadler in Paderborn, Germany).</item>
          <item>Access to the <ref target="https://tei-c.slack.com">TEI Council Slack</ref> 
            which will be the communication channel during the release process.</item>
          <item>Several hours of time. You won't be busy all the time, but the process from
            beginning to end takes several hours, especially if something goes a bit wrong and you
            have to retrace your steps. It's best to start first thing in the morning, and prepare
            to be busy all day.</item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <item> A copy of the public key that will enable you to sync the release zip with
            SourceForge. <list>
              <item>log in to the tei server at ssh tei@cchum-kvm-dockerteic.in2p3.fr (this requires that you've completed
                the other public key step above).</item>
              <item><code>cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub</code> and copy the contents to the clipboard.</item>
              <item>paste the result into a text editor and remove any linebreaks added by the
                terminal.</item>
              <item>copy-paste the result into https://sourceforge.net/auth/shell_services</item>
            </list> What this does is to enable you (when logged in as tei to tei-c.org) to connect
            to SourceForge (as your SF user) to upload the release files. </item>

          <item>Test it by trying to log into SourceForge via ssh from the tei-c.org server:<lb/>
            <code>ssh sfuser,tei@frs.sourceforge.net</code><lb/> where "sfuser" is your SourceForge
            user name. You should not see a prompt for a password (because of the ssh keys you have
            set up). Instead, you should immediately see <q>Welcome! This is a restricted Shell
              Account. You can only copy files to/from here.</q> If you see this, then everything is
            set up correctly.</item>

        </list>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="issueHandlingGuidelines">
          <head>Issue Handling Recommendations</head>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>Assign tickets to release milestone</item>
        <item>Use ticket reference in any commits addressing or fixing the issue</item>
        <item>At least for the final commit addressing the issue try to prepare the commit message so it can be used for Release Notes</item>
        <item>Label the issue as Release Note (green label) if it’s important to include the note about it in Release Notes</item>
        
      </list>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="releaseSteps">
        <head>Step-by-step instructions</head>

        <list type="ordered">
          <head>1-2 weeks before release:</head>
          <item>Inform the Jenkins maintainers (who may not be on the Council listserv), and the 
            TEI sysadmin, of the pending release date, so that they can be available or on-call. </item>
          <item>Ask one of the Jenkins maintainers (Peter Stadler, Martin Holmes, and Raffaele Viglianti) 
            to run a link check on the Guidelines and fix broken links in the dev branch. </item>
          <item>Ask for the TEI-C GPG key passphrase. You'll need it for signing the Debian packages. 
            (The GPG private key itself is hosted on the server at the default location.)</item>
            <!-- Revisit the above item, which was called into question during February 2020 release.
              If Debian package update is not the responsibility of release technician(s),
            and is actually handled by Peter Stadler, this step is not necessary. (JL, 2020-02-13) -->
          <item><hi rend="bold">Communicate with the TEI Council chair to make sure that the P5/ReleaseNotes/readme-X.X.X.xml 
            is compiled</hi><lb/> Normally, this will be created by the TEI Council chair at the
            point when the repository moved from its "alpha" stage to "beta", following these steps: <list>
              <item>Confirm the version number for the new release in consultation with Council. TEI
                version numbers are based on the Unicode Consortium system (<ref target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/"
                  >http://www.unicode.org/versions/</ref>) but with the first digit for major
                changes, the second for schema-changing revisions, and the third for
                non-schema-changing revisions. When the first or second digit is incremented, the
                following digit or digits is set to zero. During initial development, the version
                number is followed by "alpha"; during the pre-release checking stage, it's followed
                by "beta"; and when the release takes place, "beta" is removed and the version
                number has only digits and periods.</item>
              <item>Create the new file by cloning a previous one.</item>
              <item>Consult the git log log to check for all the significant changes since the last
                release. You can do this by opening a terminal in the root of a working copy of the
                TEI repository and running:<lb/>
                <code>git log --after=2015-08-01</code><lb/> where the date is that of the previous
                release. </item>
              <item>Add the new file into the repository with <code>git
                add</code>.</item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>At least one week before releasing, we enter a review period, during which the only
            changes made to the code to be released should be to fix errors, rather than to add new
            features. A release branch will be created by the release technician, to which ONLY
            release-blocking bug fixes and corrections to typographical errors will be pushed. The
            release technician should announce a temporary hold on pushes to the dev branch on the
            Council list, then create the branch and push it to GitHub using the following commands:
	    <lb/><code>git checkout dev</code> (make sure you start from the dev branch) or if you have the dev branch 
            checked out, <code>git status</code> in order to make sure that you have the current version and no uncommited changes.
	    <lb/><code>git checkout -b release-X.X.X</code>
	    <lb/><code>git push -u origin release-X.X.X</code></item>
	  <item>Immediately after the release branch has been pushed,
	  the release technician should inform the <ref
	  target="mailto:tei-council@lists.tei-c.org">Council
	  list</ref> and ask the maintainers of the TEI Jenkins
	  systems to add a build of the release branch so that commits
	  pushed there are properly tested, and advise them of the
	  release schedule. Remember that the maintainers (currently
	  Martin Holmes, Peter Stadler, and Raffaele Viglianti) may not be on the Council
	  list. Verify with the maintainers that all Jenkins servers are functioning properly. </item>
          <item>Pushes to the release branch should be merged back into dev regularly:
	  <lb/><code>git checkout dev</code>
	  <lb/><code>git merge release-X.X.X</code></item>
          
        </list>
        <list type="ordered">
          <head>On release day:</head>
          <item>The instructions below for Git commands are assumed to be run in the release-X.X.X
            branch unless otherwise specified. If you did not create the release branch, you can 
            set up a copy of it using the following commands:<lb/>
            <code>git pull origin</code> (to make sure your copy knows about the release branch)<lb/>
            <code>git checkout --track origin/release-X.X.X</code>
          </item>
         <item>Check the release notes for typos or other glaring errors, one last time.</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Edit the P5/VERSION file to the correct number</hi><lb/> This file
            consists only of the bare version number, followed by "alpha" or "beta":<lb/>
            <code>2.8.2beta</code><lb/> For the release process, you need to remove the letters from
            the end, leaving a pure version number:<lb/>
            <code>2.8.2</code><lb/> This changes the release from beta (or possibly alpha) to the
            actual release version number. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Announce a freeze on pushes to the release branch on the
              TEI Technical Council mailing list</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Merge the release branch into <code>released</code></hi>.  <lb/>
            <code>git checkout released</code><lb/>
            <code>git merge --no-ff -m "YOUR COMMIT MESSAGE" release-X.X.X</code></item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Repeat the steps above for the Stylesheets</hi> (have a stylesheets expert on hand 
            when releasing Stylesheets to help debug problems):
            <list type="ordered">
            <item>Edit the Stylesheets/VERSION number to the correct release number (usually just
              remove the 'a').</item>
            <item>Run <code>make log</code> to generate the changelog. Then commit the changes.</item>
            <item>Merge the release branch into <code>released</code><lb/>
              <code>git checkout released</code><lb/>
              <code>git merge --no-ff -m "YOUR COMMIT MESSAGE" release-X.X.X</code>
            </item>
          </list>
          </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Push your changes</hi> for both P5 and the Stylesheets to the git 
            repository, <code>git push origin released</code><lb/> and watch Jenkins build P5 for you.<lb/> 
            This should be the final push for this version, and it will trigger the Jenkins servers 
            to rebuild the TEI packages. As a reminder, you can find the Jenkins servers here:
            <list>
              <item><ref target="https://jenkins.tei-c.org">https://jenkins.tei-c.org</ref></item>
              <item><ref target="https://jenkins2.tei-c.org">https://jenkins2.tei-c.org</ref></item>
              <item><ref target="https://jenkins3.tei-c.org">https://jenkins3.tei-c.org</ref></item>
            </list>
            And now you wait while the Jenkins servers build the packages, keeping in mind that
            subsequent steps will require the build packages from the Paderborn Jenkins server 
            (as of February 2020). This can take a couple of hours, so be patient. 
            <!-- As of February 2020, the following sentence, which previously appeared in the TCW,
              was proven false.
              
              "All of the Jenkins servers should behave
              identically, and they should all build all three TEI packages successfully." (RV, EB, JL, 2020-02-13) -->
            <hi rend="bold">Note</hi>: The P5 and Stylesheets builds have reciprocal dependencies,
            so the first build of either the Stylesheets or the Guidelines may fail just because
            there isn't yet a current build of the other for it to use. This isn't a cause for
            panic, but it may mean that (e.g.) the Stylesheets build needs to run twice. In particular,
	    the Stylesheets build may fail after the TEI release is complete, so it is better to wait
	    until the TEI release is complete before doing the Stylesheets release. (Council is considering 
	    changing how the dependency is managed).</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Ensure all changes have been committed, built, and successfully
              passed tests on the continuous integration server</hi><lb/> When all builds have
            completed on all Jenkins servers, click on the job number of the last build for each of the
            three TEI jobs to make sure that it was triggered by the commit that you made in the
            previous step (you should see your own commit message on the build page). Make sure that
            all builds were successful (they should have green balls next to them). In the case of red balls,
            indicating a failed build, seek support via the TEI Council Slack. </item>
          <item>
            <hi rend="bold">Log into TEI server and run the tei-install.sh script:</hi><lb/>
            Log into the TEI server via <code>ssh tei@cchum-kvm-dockerteic.in2p3.fr</code> 
            and fetch the current version of the install script by issuing 
            <code>curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI/dev/P5/Utilities/tei-install.sh -o ~/tei-install.sh</code>.
            <lb/> (If you'll need to tweak that script later during the install process please make 
            sure to feed the changes back to the original script in the TEI repo.) 
            <lb/> Do the following three steps: <list>
              <item>Install on tei-c.org: <code>./tei-install.sh --package=TEIP5 --version=X.X.X
                  --sfuser=username --install</code> and then <emph>go test the version this puts in
                  the Vault</emph>.</item>
              <item>If that looks good and everyone agrees then: <code>./tei-install.sh
                  --package=TEIP5 --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --makecurrent</code> and
                then <emph>test that it appears on website correctly</emph>.</item>
              <item>If the website looks right then: <code>./tei-install.sh --package=TEIP5
                  --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --upload</code> and then move on to the next
                step.</item>
            </list>
            In each of these steps, replace the Xs with your release version. Supply your
            SourceForge user name, and type your SourceForge password when prompted. By default, the
            script will pull the release package from the first Jenkins server, but you can supply
            the URL of the other server if necessary with the --Jenkins parameter, e.g. 
            --Jenkins=http://jenkins2.tei-c.org/. Make sure the script completes successfully each time 
            changing the final parameter from --install, to --makecurrent, and then --upload. </item>
          
          <item><hi rend="bold">Repeat the steps above for the Stylesheets</hi>, remembering that the version number is the Stylesheets version, which will be different from
            the Guidelines version:
            <lb/><code>./tei-install.sh --package=Stylesheets
              --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --install</code>
            <lb/><code>./tei-install.sh --package=Stylesheets
              --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --makecurrent</code>
            <lb/><code>./tei-install.sh --package=Stylesheets
              --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --upload</code>
            <lb/>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Check the TEI website and all downloadable files are displaying the
              correct version</hi><lb/> Everything should now be done, so go to <ref
              target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">the newly
              released version on the TEI site</ref> and browse the Guidelines. Check that your
            version number is displayed in the footer of the page, and check that at least one
            change made since the last release is being reflected online. </item>
          
          <item><hi rend="bold">Update <ref target="https://roma.tei-c.org/">Roma</ref>, 
            <ref target="https://romabeta.tei-c.org/">Romabeta</ref>, and <ref target="https://oxgarage.tei-c.org/">OxGarage</ref></hi> 
            <lb/>Change to the directory <code>~/repos/infrastructure/humanum</code> and issue the script 
            <code>docker-update.sh</code> for every service, i.e. 
            <list>
              <item><code># docker-update.sh roma</code></item>
              <item><code># docker-update.sh romabeta</code></item>
              <item><code># docker-update.sh oxgarage</code></item>
            </list>
            NB: Every invocation might take some time but each should succesfully finish with the notification 
            "Creating $CONTAINER$ ... done" 
          </item>

          <item>
            <hi rend="bold">Make your release the default downloadable version from
              Sourceforge</hi><lb/> Go to the SourceForge site (<ref
                target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/tei/files/TEI-P5-all/">https://sourceforge.net/projects/tei/files/TEI-P5-all/</ref>),
            log in, and click the information button on your new release. Make it the default download for all
            operating systems. Now make sure that the main Download button links to your package. </item>

          <item>
            <hi rend="bold">Update tags on GitHub</hi><lb/> Every time a new release is made, a
            "tag" is created consisting of a pointer to the state of the P5 tree at release time.
            You can do this from the command line on your own computer. Before moving forward, be
            sure to do a git pull and update your released branch. Then, still in the released
            branch, do:<lb/>
            <code>git tag -a P5_Release_X.X.X -m "Release X.X.X of the TEI Guidelines."</code><lb/>
            where X.X.X is your new release. Then<lb/>
            <code>git push origin P5_Release_X.X.X</code>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Make a Release on GitHub</hi><lb/> Go to the TEI Tags page at <ref
            target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/tags">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/tags</ref> on GitHub. You should
            see the tag you just pushed there. Click on it and then click on "Edit Release". Add a link to the release notes README, which should be at
            https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/readme-X.X.X.html, into the text box. Add a copy of the zipped
            release by downloading it from <ref
              target="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/"
              >https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/</ref> and then uploading it to the release page. </item>
          
          <item><hi rend="bold">Close/Add GitHub Milestones</hi><lb/> Go to the Milestones page of both the 
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/milestones">Stylesheets</ref> and the 
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/milestones">Guidelines</ref> repo. Add new Milestones by 
            incrementing the minor version number part and move all open issues from the current Milestone to the new one.
            (If Council already decided on the next release date (unlikely) you can add the date to the new Milestone. Otherwise leave empty.)
            Finally, close the current Milestone.</item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Update the Debian Package repository with the new release</hi><lb/>
            The TEI Debian packages are regularily created during each Jenkins build. 
            For each release you need to update the TEI Debian repository at 
            <ref target="http://packages.tei-c.org/deb/">http://packages.tei-c.org/deb/</ref> 
            which can be done by simply running <code>ant</code> on the TEI server within the 
            <code>/data/debian-packages</code> directory. 
            (This directory is cloned from <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI-apt-repo">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI-apt-repo</ref>)
            <emph>Since the repository index needs to be signed, you'll need the passphrase for the GPG key.</emph> 
            Make sure you've received it in advance! 
            <lb/>Once the process has finished and the repo is updated, the page at <ref target="http://packages.tei-c.org/deb/">http://packages.tei-c.org/deb/</ref>
            should reflect the changes immediately. If not, try to restart the NGINX Docker container that serves this directory 
            with <code>docker restart debian-packages</code>.
            <!--<lb/>Another caveat: <code>ant</code> fails to fetch the packages via HTTPS when 
            running an outdated Java VM. Make sure to set the environment variable <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
            to some appropriate version! At present <code>export JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/jvm/java-11-openjdk-amd64</code>
            will do.-->
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Update the list of previous releases of P5</hi>, which is found at <ref
            target="https://tei-c.org/guidelines/p5/#section-2">https://tei-c.org/guidelines/p5/#section-2</ref>.<lb/>
            If you have editing privileges on the TEI WordPress on tei-c.org, add the new release to the top of the release table. If not, ask one of the
            other Council members who does (currently Martina Scholger and Hugh Cayless) to make the change. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Update the oXygen-ready distribution of TEI.</hi><lb/> This involves
            building the new package of oxygen-tei, and then updating the distribution file on the
            TEI server so that the oXygen software knows about the new release. You may request to
            hand this off to one of the maintainers (currently Syd Bauman, James Cummings, or Martin
            Holmes) to do this for you if you're not familiar with the project. <list>
              <item>Check that you have ant (at least version 1.8) installed on your machine.</item>
              <item>Check that the latest versions of the TEI Stylesheets and TEI P5 packages are
                available for download from the SourceForge Files section, since the oxygen-tei
                update/upload script retrieves them from there.</item>
              <item>Check out or update a local copy of the source code from <ref
                  target="https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei"
                  >https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei</ref> to your local system.</item>
              <item>Make sure the build script knows where to find your oxygen.jar file (from the
                Oxygen installed on your system) by copying the file into
                  <code>oxygen-tei/lib</code> or symlinking it.</item>
              <item>cd into the oxygen-tei folder (it should contain folders called "frameworks" and
                "jenkins").</item>
              <item>Run the ant build process with the "release" parameter: <lb/>
                <code>ant release</code><lb/> This builds the plugin using the latest stable
                versions of P5 and the Stylesheets, then offers to upload the result to the TEI's
                SourceForge repo to become a release of the TEI-maintained version of the plugin.
                This also creates an updated updateSite.oxygen file, by retrieving the latest
                updateSite.oxygen file from the tei-c.org site, and asks the user to provide the new
                version number before creating a new version of updateSite.oxygen. It also offers to
                upload that file to tei-c.org, if the user has shell access. </item>
            </list>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Inform the TEI Technical Council Chair so they can announce the
              release</hi><lb/> Once you are sure that everything is working correctly, inform the
            Council Chair. They will announce the release to the TEI-L mailing list, including the
            text of P5/ReleaseNotes/readme-X.X.X.xml in plain text form (which can be generated
            using the "readme" profile for teitotxt), and place an announcement on the Text Encoding
            Initiative Newsfeed blog in the category of 'News'. </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Lift the freeze on committing changes to the repository</hi><lb/>
            Write to the TEI Council list and let them know that they can once again start
            committing changes to the repository.</item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Increment the build number for the next release cycle</hi><lb/>
            Recalling how release preparation requires confirmation of version number,
            use your best judgment to determine the version number for the next release (in consultation with Council,
            if possible). TEI version numbers are based on the Unicode Consortium system (<ref
              target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/">http://www.unicode.org/versions/</ref>) but with the first
            digit for major changes, the second for schema-changing revisions, and the third for
            non-schema-changing revisions. When the first or second digit is incremented, the
            following digit or digits is set to zero. 
            
            <!-- Revisit version control instructions at May 2020 F2F (JL, 2020-02-13) -->
            
            After the release process has been completed, the release number for both P5 and the
            Stylesheets needs to be updated. On the dev branch, edit the P5/VERSION file and the Stylesheets/VERSION
            file to the correct numbers. These files contain nothing except the bare version number. 
            It should be incremented appropriately, and "a" added to the end of it, so if for example 
            the release was number 2.8.0, you would change the number in the file to:<lb/>
            <code>2.9.0a</code><lb/> signifying that the versions built subsequent to the release
            are now in the alpha stage. </item>

        </list>

      </div>

    </body>


  </text>
</TEI>

