<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
$LastChangedDate: 2012-08-09$
$LastChangedBy: rebeccawelzenbach$
$LastChangedRevision: 0001$
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Style Guide for Editing the TEI Guidelines</title>
        <author>Rebecca Welzenbach</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Technical Council</publisher>
        <date>2012</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>The first draft of this document was created by moving the "House Style: preferred
          orthography" and "House Style: notes on usage" sections from TCW20, "How to Edit the TEI
          Guidelines" to their own document, TCW24, which will serve as a full style guide for the
          Guidelines.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-03-11" who="HAC">Added egXML guidance</change>
      <change when="2013-09-02" who="KSH">Link to BCP 14</change>
      <change when="2013-03-16" who="KSH">Fixed ptrs</change>
      <change when="2013-02-01" who="KSH">"TEI header" is preferred</change>
      <change when="2013-01-27" who="KSH">Explained -ize vs. -ise. Also a markup fix.</change>
      <change when="2012-01-08" who="KSH">desc's for attributes should also be verbal phrases</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28" who="KSH">Added note about desc elements containing verbal 
        phrases; some light copyediting</change>
      <change when="2012-08-09" who="RAW">Adding prose about use of first-person/"we" and
        second-person/"you" in the Guidelines. </change>
      <change when="2012-08-06" who="RAW">started first draft: moving sections from TCW20, "How to
        Edit the TEI Guidelines" to their own document. Re-ordered some sections, proofread, added
        some examples, and added discussion of hyphenation. </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This document aims to capture decisions about House Style for writing and editing the TEI
        Guidelines, in order to maintain consistency throughout the Guidelines.</p>
      <div xml:id="house-style-tone-and-voice">
        <head>Tone and voice</head>
        <p>The Guidelines are a reference manual, not a tutorial. You should not talk down to the
          reader, but assume they have a reasonably well-informed knowledge of the subjects under
          discussion. Make copious use of cross references, rather than repetition.</p>
        <p>Bear in mind however that your reader may not have English as their first language. Avoid
          needlessly complex sentences and unnecessarily obscure terminology.</p>
        <p>Choose clarity and concision over adherence to any particular voice. However, you should
          be careful in your use of the first person, avoiding the implication that a community of
          scholars, or the whole TEI community, takes a certain view. The use of "we" is appropriate
          in passages of formal textual exposition, where "we" refers to both the reader and the
          authorial voice. For instance: "Each chapter of the Guidelines presents a group of related
          elements, and also defines a corresponding set of declarations, which we call a
          module."</p>
        <p>Avoid the use of a first-person authorial voice that does not include the reader as part
          of "we." For instance: "We do not describe them in detail here," which refers to a
          particular editorial decision made by the authors of the Guidelines. In this case, "They
          are not described in detail here" is preferred.</p>
        <p>As a test, ask yourself whether the material being asserted, typically a technical term
          or usage, is something the reader is expected to internalize and use themselves
          thereafter. If so, use "we." If not, it is more appropriate to use the passive voice.</p>
        <p>In general, avoid imperative constructions ("you should..."). However, key words like 
          "should", "must", "must not", "recommended", etc. should be used in accordance with 
          <ref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp14">BCP 14</ref>.</p>
        
      </div>
      <div xml:id="house-style-usage">
        <head>General notes on usage</head>
        <p>This is a list of notes on usage preferences and conventions, which we expect to expand
          over time.</p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>Gender-neutral pronouns</label>
          <item>We prefer the usage "they", "their" etc. where the third person singular is
            required, but gender is unspecified. For instance: "The encoder may follow their own
            preference here." This is less ungainly than "his/her" etc. </item>
          <label>Technical terms</label>
          <item>Make sure that technical terms are glossed on their first appearance. For instance,
            XML-related terminology should be introduced in the chapter on XML. If you want to
            provide other references, do so as footnotes, using the <gi>note</gi> element.</item>
          <label>References</label>
          <item>Provide bibliographic citations for any other standards (etc) referenced, following
            the existing style. Do not introduce bibliographic citations simply in order to
            demonstrate your learning. </item>
          <label>Descriptions in specifications</label>
          <item>The description of an element, attribute, model class, or attribute class contained in 
            <gi>desc</gi> should always be a verbal phrase beginning with a present-tense verb 
            ("contains a ...", "groups together ...", etc.)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="house-style-naming-conventions">
        <head>Naming conventions</head>
        <p>TEI naming conventions have evolved over time, but remain fairly consistent. </p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>generic identifiers</label>
          <item>Element and attribute identifiers should be a single natural language word in
            lowercase if possible. For instance: <gi>bibl</gi>. If more than one word is conjoined
            to form a name, then the first letter of the second and any subsequent word should be
            uppercased. For instance: <gi>biblStruct</gi>. Hyphens, underscores, dots etc are not
            used within element or attribute names. </item>
          <label>class names</label>
          <item>Class names are made up three parts: a name, constructed like an element name, with
            a prefix and optionally a suffix. The prefix is one of <code>model.</code> or
            <code>att.</code> and indicates whether this is a model or an attribute class. The
            suffix, if present, is used to indicate subclassing. For example
            <ident>att.linking.foo</ident> is the <ident>foo</ident> subclass of the attribute
            class <ident>att.linking</ident></item>
          <label>xml:id values</label>
          <item>The conventions for these vary somewhat. Most of the older chapters of the
            guidelines have consistently constructed identifiers, derived from the individual
            section headings. Identifiers must be provided for:- <list>
              <item>every <gi>div</gi>, whether or not it is explicitly linked to elsewhere</item>
              <item>every bibliographic reference in the <ident>BIB.xml</ident> file</item>
            </list></item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="house-style-capitalization">
        <head>Capitalization of headings</head>
        <p>Use title case as defined in the <title level="m">Chicago Manual of Style</title> for 
          all headings (i.e. all text in <gi>head</gi> elements that occur as children of <gi>div</gi>
          elements). </p>
        
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="house-style-orthography">
        <head>Preferred orthography</head>
        <p>The goal of these rules is to avoid inconsistency, and also (wherever possible) to avoid
          producing text which is markedly either British or American English. For example, use the 
          "-ize" suffix instead of "-ise" for words that are a Latinized version of a Greek suffix because 
          while both spellings are given in the Oxford English Dictionary, only the "-ize" form is used 
          in American English. The following table
          lists the preferred word-spacing and hyphenation for a number of frequently-used terms: <table>
            <row role="label">
              <cell>Word or Term</cell>
              <cell>Authority/explanation</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>code point (n.); code-point (adj.)</cell>
              <cell>UCG [discussed on TEI Council list]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>cross-reference</cell>
              <cell>MW, OED</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>data set</cell>
              <cell>OED</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>datatype</cell>
              <cell>[OED, ORDS have 'data type', but Guidelines consistently use single word dozens
                of places]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>email (not *e-mail)</cell>
              <cell>commoner usage; consistency with JTEI; name of TEI element; bug #664</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>end-tag</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>GitHub</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>TEI header; the &lt;teiHeader&gt;</cell>
              <cell>[discussed on TEI Council list in January/February 2013]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>high-level (adj.)</cell>
              <cell>MW, OED</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>line break</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>lowercase/uppercase</cell>
              <cell>MW, ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>proofread</cell>
              <cell>MW, OED</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>SourceForge</cell>
              <cell></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>start-tag</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>stylesheet</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>typeface</cell>
              <cell>MW</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>the Web</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>web page</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>web site</cell>
              <cell> ORDS, OED</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>well-formed (even in a predicate usage: "the XML is well-formed")</cell>
              <cell>W3CXML</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>whitespace</cell>
              <cell>ORDS</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </p>
        <p>The abbreviations above refer to the following list of authorities, which may also be
          consulted for other vexed issues: <list type="gloss">
            <label> CMS</label>
            <item> Chicago Manual of Style, 15th ed.</item>
            <label> MW</label>
            <item> Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary, 11th ed.</item>
            <label> OED</label>
            <item> Oxford English Dictionary, 2d ed. online (<ptr target="http://dictionary.oed.com/"
            />)</item>
            <label> ODE</label>
            <item> Oxford Dictionary of English (aka NODE), 2d ed.</item>
            <label> ORDS</label>
            <item> O'Reilly Default Stylesheet, <ptr
              target="http://www.oreilly.com/oreilly/author/stylesheet.html"/></item>
            <label> UCG</label>
            <item> Unicode Consortium Glossary, <ptr target="http://unicode.org/glossary/"/></item>
            <label> W3CXML</label>
            <item> W3C XML Recommendation, <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/"/></item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="house-style-punctuation">
        <head>Punctuation</head>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>Em dashes</label>
          <item>Only em dashes should be used parenthetically (do not use en dashes or hyphens for
            this purpose). There should be no spaces around them when they are used in this way. The
            only exception to the above (currently) is where we refer to the titles of ISO
            documents, where we must follow the ISO practice of using spaces.</item>
          <label>En dashes</label>
          <item>En dashes should be used for numerical ranges such as dates, page-ranges, etc. En
            dashes should not have spaces around them.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="house-style-egXML">
        <head>Conventions in <gi>egXML</gi></head>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>Elided elements</label>
          <item>Very often, examples will omit markup, even markup that would ordinarily be necessary
            for the example to be valid. Such elisions should be marked with an ellipsis inside a
            comment, usually on its own line, thus: <lb/>
            <code>&lt;!-- ... --&gt;</code>.</item>
          <label>Elided text</label>
          <item>Similarly, examples often omit text that doesn't serve the purpose of the example.
            Such text is to be marked with an ellipsis in square brackets, thus: <code>[...]</code>.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="appendix">
        <head>Some other (mostly superseded) documents on the topic of style</head>
        
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><idno>TEI ED W9</idno>
            <title>Points of Style For Drafts of TEI Guidelines</title>,
            <date>2 Mar 1990</date>
            (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw09.gml">in Waterloo Script format</ref>)
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl>
            <idno>TEI ED W11</idno>
            <title>Notes on House Style</title>,
            <date>14 Sep 1992</date>
            (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw11.gml">in Waterloo script</ref>,
            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw11.txt">formatted text</ref>)
          </bibl>
          
          
          <bibl><idno>TEI ED W55</idno>
            <title>Form for Draft Chapters of the TEI Guidelines</title>,
            <date>5 june 1996</date>
            (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.tei">in TEI P2 format</ref>,
            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.htm">in HTML format</ref>,
            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.odd">in ODD format</ref>)
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl><idno>TEI ED W57</idno>
            <title>Procedures for Correcting Errors in the TEI Guidelines</title>,
            <date>July 23, 1994</date>
            (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw57.tei">in TEI P2 format</ref>,
            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw57.htm">in HTML format</ref>)
          </bibl>
          
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>