<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TCW27: Procedure for handling practices that are no longer recommended or
               deprecated</title>
            <author>Kevin Hawkins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013-05-16</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>freely available</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Manually reformatted from <ref>http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Practices_no_longer_recommended_or_now_deprecated</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-06-21" who="RV">Added guidelines for changes only affecting ODD customizations.</change>
         <change when="2014-01-01" who="KSH">Removed step about creating Schematron warning: Syd says they're generated automatically based on presence of @validUntil.</change>
         <change when="2013-12-26" who="KSH">Added standard wording for Schematron warnings and instruction to notify TEI-L of planned deprecations</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="KSH">Copyediting</change>
         <change when="2013-05-16" who="KSH">Added more missing markup from wiki</change>
         <change when="2013-05-16" who="KSH">Added link to tcw09 (Birnbaum doctrine)</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
        <head>Procedure for handling practices that are no longer recommended or deprecated</head>
            <p>At its April 2013 face-to-face meeting in Providence, the Technical Council agreed to
               the following policy for handling practices that are "no longer recommended" or
               "deprecated".</p>

            <div>
               <head>No longer recommended</head>

               <p>While the TEI Guidelines often offer more than one way of encoding a particular
                  phenomenon, in this case the Council agrees to identify a preferred method without
                  making any definite plans to remove the non-preferred way from the Guidelines. In
                  this case:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The <gi>remarks</gi> element is used in the spec to indicate the preferred
                     practice.</item>
                  <item>The prose in one or more chapters is revised to indicate this preferred
                     practice. Examples showing the non-preferred practice are maintained but
                     preferably only in the section of the Guidelines where that element or
                     attribute is discussed, not in passing elsewhere.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            
            <div>
               <head>Deprecated</head>
               
               <p>Following  the <ref target="https://tei-c.org/activities/council/working/tcw09-backward-compatibility-and-the-maintenance-of-the-text-encoding-initiative-guidelines/">Birnbaum doctrine</ref>, the Council has made the serious decision to
                  break backwards compatibility by changing the content model of an element or class
                  to remove an element or attribute, or to remove an element or attribute entirely
                  from the Guidelines. In this case:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The appropriate specification is given a <att>validUntil</att> attribute indicating the intended date 
                     after which the specification will be withdrawn. Specifications which can be deprecated this way are all 
                     members of the class <ident type="class">att.deprecated</ident>.</item>
                  <item>An announcement is sent to TEI-L that the Technical Council has decided to 
                     deprecate elementName and will drop it as early as YYYY-MM-DD. If anyone strongly objects, 
                     they should reply to the list so that the Council might reconsider.</item>
                  <item>Any examples of the deprecated practice are removed from the Guidelines, and
                     any prose recommending them is reworded as appropriate.</item>
                  <item>We will try to remember to include a mention of the deprecation in the
                     release notes created for the following release.</item>
               </list>
               
               <p>After the date specified in <att>validUntil</att>:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The element or attribute is actually removed from the spec.</item>
               </list>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Changes only affecting ODD customizations</head>

               <p>This is an addition agreed on the 2023-11-10 TEI council call, formalizing an already established practice.</p>
               
               <p>Occasionally, some changes in the TEI source do not result in a deprecation, but will still affect ODD customizations. 
                  For example, in Release 2.3.0, <gi>abbr</gi> stopped defining its own @type attribute and became members of from att.typed.
                  As a result, an ODD modifying att.typed would affect <gi>abbr</gi>, a possible unwanted consequence of this change.</p>
               <p>In these circumstances, a deprecation period is not required; however, the change must be listed in the release notes.</p>
            </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
