<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>TEI Council: Workload and Guidelines for Resignation</title>
                <author>Syd Bauman</author>
                <author>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</author>
                <author>Jessica Lu</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020-06-29</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>freely available</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born-digital document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>TEI Council: Workload and Guidelines for Resignation</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Workload</head>
                    <p> Once elected, your voluntary membership on the TEI Council is both an
                        opportunity and a responsibility. The TEI and its community rely upon the
                        Council’s consistent attention and engagement. While the Council shares and
                        distributes duties among its members, each individual Council member can
                        expect to devote, at a minimum: <list>
                            <item>Several scheduled and self-paced hours, monthly, to “orientation”
                                and mentorship during the first year of Council service;</item>
                            <item>3 scheduled hours, monthly, to virtual conferencing for the
                                duration of your elected term;</item>
                            <item>4+ self-paced hours, monthly, to addressing tickets and other
                                Council tasks (e.g. server maintenance, listserv correspondence,
                                special projects, etc.) after your orientation and for the duration
                                of your elected term;</item>
                            <item>10 days, annually, to two face-to-face Council meetings and
                                associated travel (expenses reimbursed).</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Furthermore, Councilmembers are encouraged to submit original work for peer
                        review and presentation at the annual TEI Conference and Members’
                        meeting.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Resignation</head>
                    <p> Occasionally, a Council member may be unable to meet the demands of their
                        work on the Council. <lb/>While temporary absences (due to illness,
                        financial or personal hardship, etc.), are certainly acceptable, Council
                        members should communicate their needs for accommodations. Council members
                        who must disengage from Council work for an extended period are asked to
                        vacate their elected position in a timely manner. </p>
                    <p> Resignation should be strongly considered if: <list>
                            <item>A Council member is unable to attend all-Council virtual
                                conferences for three consecutive months, or is unable to attend at
                                least half of the all-Council virtual conferences over the course of
                                a six-month period.</item>
                            <item>A Council member is unable to assume responsibility for any
                                regular Council tasks (including, but not limited to, minutes
                                review, ticket triage, and ticket review) for three consecutive
                                months.</item>
                            <item>A Council member is unable to attend both the annual face-to-face
                                all-Council meeting and the annual TEI Conference and Members’
                                Meeting in a given year.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Process</head>
                        <p>When Council members are considering resigning from their elected
                            position, we ask that they: <list>
                                <item>Discuss the situation with their mentor or another Council
                                    member first <list>
                                        <item>a) to discover whether accommodations other than their
                                            departure might be made that would mutually benefit both
                                            the member and the Council; and</item>
                                        <item>b) to ensure that Council can prepare for their
                                            absence and reassign their work.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>Submit an official message of resignation from their elected
                                    position via email to the Council chair.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>A Council member’s resignation will activate a provision of the <ref target="https://tei-c.org/about/bylaws/">TEI-Consortium Bylaws</ref> and may initiate the process for a special election or
                            appointment to fill the vacated position. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
